<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://zandyne.xyz</link>
      <description></description>
      <generator>Zola</generator>
      <language>en</language>
      <atom:link href="https://zandyne.xyz/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
      <lastBuildDate>Sun, 31 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
          <title>Cool media I experienced this year</title>
          <pubDate>Sun, 31 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Unknown</author>
          <link>https://zandyne.xyz/blog/2023media/</link>
          <guid>https://zandyne.xyz/blog/2023media/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://zandyne.xyz/blog/2023media/">&lt;p&gt;2023 was a great year for me in terms of branching out and experiencing new stuff. Here&#x27;s some notable works that left a big impact on me this year. Not everything here is a perfect 10 or even something I particularly like.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inland Empire (2006)&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;ve been reluctant to really finish this movie because it&#x27;s like 3 hours and I was told the experience is unnerving in general. However, I&#x27;ve eaten through most of David Lynch&#x27;s discography and this was like the only thing left. Inland Empire explores the relationship movies have with reality and the way the gap between the two can slowly be broken and the line can be blurred. Without spoiling, I think it&#x27;s an excellent evolution of the surrealist direction and theme that Mulholland Drive was attempting. I do not recommend this as your first Lynch flick, it should be like your fifth.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Like a Dragon Gaiden: The Man Who Erased His Name (2023)&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Already talked about this on my &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.backloggd.com&#x2F;u&#x2F;zandyne_&#x2F;review&#x2F;1139880&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Backloggd&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; but Gaiden is a really enjoyable love letter that shows how good RGG Studio has gotten at the Yakuza formula. It&#x27;s a love letter to the series as a whole, and ties everything up in a really satisfying conclusion. The final boss is top 5 in the series, easy.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Drakengard (2003)&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taro at his prime. Postmodern commentary on the increasing indulgence of violence in mainstream video games back in the 2000s, and while a lot of that critique seems silly nowadays, the experience as a whole is so surreal and feels straight out of Eva or Berserk at points. You should experience this.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Digital Devil Saga duology (2004-2005)&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Atlus R&amp;amp;D&#x27;s crown jewel, written and designed at their absolute prime as a studio, putting out the best content they ever have. Digital Devil Saga is heavy-handed and very straightforward in its theming, but Atlus has never been known for their subtlety. DDS manages to tie Hindu mythology into an interesting science-fiction framework exploring the worth of AI and breaking the cycle of violence all too common in humanity. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Press Turn system from Nocturne evolves here and provides some of the most satisfying turn-based combat, ever. Kazuma Kaneko pumped out some of the most interesting designs he ever has with the uniquely stylized Atma forms of the cast.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kareshi Kanojo no Jijou (1998)&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kare Kano&#x27;s anime adaptation is peak Hideaki Anno, taking advantage of all the directorial tricks he grew accustomed to in past works like Evangelion and Nadia. I don&#x27;t think the anime &amp;quot;falls off&amp;quot; at all, and instead feel it maintains a pretty consistent level of quality. I think this is a great example of a solid director elevating the experience of source material. I&#x27;ve since then read the manga and it doesn&#x27;t hit nearly as hard for me as it does with that Gainax touch. No respect to Masami Tsuda, though.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rule of Rose (2006)&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unique in its child cast and grim tone and subject matter. Gameplay made me want to blow my brains out, but I understand why this game&#x27;s so cherished.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Armored Core VI: Fires of Rubicon (2023)&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outside of some balancing issues, this is one of the most satisfying games released this year and addresses the itch I&#x27;ve had in my brain for years wanting more Armored Core.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Oyasumi Punpun (2007)&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not the kind of thing I would normally experience in manga form, but I&#x27;m glad I did. Punpun is incredibly thoughtful and intelligent in its understanding of social dynamics, abuse, trauma, and coming of age. Don&#x27;t read this unless you specifically are open to getting kicked in the nuts emotionally.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scott Pilgrim (2004)&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, this is a reread, but I don&#x27;t care. Revisiting this has been absolutely great, as I&#x27;m able to relate to the subject matter here way more than I did as a kid. O&#x27;Malley&#x27;s Nerd References and Video Game Callbacks might seem corny in current year, but it feels a lot more genuine when you consider the time period it was written in. The entire experience feels very genuine and explores two flawed people trying to mend together a relationship. I love it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Yakuza 6 is good, actually</title>
          <pubDate>Sat, 23 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Unknown</author>
          <link>https://zandyne.xyz/blog/rgg6/</link>
          <guid>https://zandyne.xyz/blog/rgg6/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://zandyne.xyz/blog/rgg6/">&lt;p&gt;Looking at SEGA&#x27;s Yakuza franchise, there&#x27;s a point where the series shifted away from its traditional approach of last-minute twists and tried punching above to have more &amp;quot;tame&amp;quot;, grounded storytelling.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yakuza 0 in 2015 was probably the most obvious shift -- it&#x27;s widely loved for having a very airtight and well-paced narrative that doesn&#x27;t really slip in too many narrative frustrations or eleventh-hour plot twists. While I felt the earlier style had its charm, the series took a bold step forward with Zero.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#x27;s look at the new content that came out after that game:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yakuza 6&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Judgment&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yakuza 7 (Like a Dragon)&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lost Judgment&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Like a Dragon Gaiden&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#x27;t know about you, but I&#x27;d argue these five games have more reserved and overall better writing than a lot of the stuff that game before. Yokoyama and new writer Tsuyoshi Furuta have played a big role in causing that shift.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furuta&#x27;s first game, believe it or not, was Yakuza 6.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;6 marked the first time the franchise would shift to a wholly new engine since Kenzan. Every game that released from the studio from Kenzan to Fist of the North Star: Lost Paradise uses various iterations on the same PS3-era engine. While I think it looks good, 6 looked... gorgeous.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#x27;s Yakuza 3&#x27;s iteration of Kamurocho.
&lt;img src=&quot;&#x2F;kamuro3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;I mean, it&#x27;s alright&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#x27;s 6:
&lt;img src=&quot;&#x2F;kamuro6.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;It was perfect.&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is from the game&#x27;s demo.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#x27;s a huge jump in terms of realism. Textures are larger, movements are more natural, and transitions between entering locations, leaving, doing whatever are all seamless. Everything feels fresh and new in a way that the series really needed. While the old PS3 engine is still perfectly competent, it&#x27;s limited in terms of how well it can scale up on modern hardware. Which brings me to my first point, and this is something that 6 still does the best in the entire series:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;yakuza-6-is-able-to-avoid-the-jarring-disconnect-between-substory-minigame-and-main-story-presentation&quot;&gt;Yakuza 6 is able to avoid the jarring disconnect between substory, minigame, and main story presentation.&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Everything is voiced.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; All of the substories feel less like lower effort padding and instead feel like purposeful parts of a whole. There&#x27;s no ticking text box sound -- everyone talks to and addresses Kiryu and he responds in turn. It&#x27;s reminiscent of Yakuza 1 and 2&#x27;s insistence on having several substories with main-story presentation and cutscenes. Just.. absolutely great stuff. The game has a very solid attention to detail with the world it&#x27;s fleshed out.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;it-s-a-game-about-kiryu-s-life&quot;&gt;It&#x27;s a game about Kiryu&#x27;s life.&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yakuza 6 is able to explore aspects of Kiryu&#x27;s life in a way that doesn&#x27;t feel particularly heavy handed. Whether it&#x27;s the similarity of the Hirose family to Yakuza 3&#x27;s Ryudo family, Hirose himself being eerily similar to Kazama, and the core theme throughout the series of fatherhood, 6 is aiming for something higher than simple fanservice.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that&#x27;s what frustrates me about the way a lot of people perceive this game -- they act as if this series is starved of constant fanservice, self-fellating, and references to past glup shittos.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seriously, let&#x27;s look at the last few games that dropped before 6. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yakuza 5 does have a lot of fresh, new material, but the majority of the characters appearing are veterans. It feels the need to pull out the ensemble cast accumulated over years for its very grandiose story.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ishin is literally raw fanservice and a large part of its appeal is quite literally just seeing past, sometimes deceased characters play different roles. Here&#x27;s Ryuji, and Mine, and Akiyama, and Aizawa and Baba and Saejima and Majima...
If you&#x27;re starved for cast interactions, there&#x27;s more than enough here to last you hours.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yakuza 0 thankfully has a lot of fresh, new characters written just for its prequel, but at the same time it&#x27;s very much so tied to Yakuza 1 and its cast. Tons of characters throughout the series have younger versions here. It&#x27;s quite literally a 10th anniversary game for the franchise and I can understand why it felt the need to honor the franchise&#x27;s cast one more time.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...So now we go into Yakuza 6. Don&#x27;t you think that an overbearing presence of the main cast is a little too much for a game like this? Again -- it&#x27;s a game mainly about Kazuma Kiryu&#x27;s life, not him and his friends. They don&#x27;t cease to exist, but there&#x27;s a reason the game shifts to an entirely fresh location with limited interaction from past characters.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;japan-and-its-struggle-to-accept-the-future&quot;&gt;Japan and its struggle to accept the future&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;6 being a massive technological jump fits its themes perfectly. The core conflict that has a bunch of old men throwing tantrums is the potential exposure of a &amp;quot;version 2&amp;quot; of a legendary WW2 battleship to the world. I&#x27;m very confused why so many people don&#x27;t seem to get the political relevance of the big ass boat towards the end of the game. It&#x27;s the perfect representation of stubborn wrinkly ass niggas clinging to an old Japan long gone.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The beautiful city of Onomichi has a festering, disgusting mold growing underneath it, and what hit me is the scathing commentary this represents as a whole for Japan. Minoru Daidoji has literally shit on the ground and a bunch of grown ass adults are trying to cover it up and make sure nobody knows. I can&#x27;t really think of any other plot point in this entire franchise that is such an actively politically charged statement. Ishin, the game quite literally ABOUT the Bakumatsu period and leading into the Meiji Restoration, has the most milquetoast nationalist messaging ever in comparison. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only thing that really feels similar in approach is the Empty Lot in 0 -- a perfect representation of bubble-era Japan and its obsessive greed and corruption; its absolutely absurd real estate market. Buckets of blood were spilled just to reclaim a tiny patch of land. But 6&#x27;s commentary is &lt;em&gt;contemporary&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. A lot of people still reminisce Imperial Japan and I would not be surprised to see real life skeletons in the closet if we examined a lot of public figures and areas in the country.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outside of the secret of Onomichi, Kiryu gets out of self-imposed jail literally greeted with the enormous shift in technology over the years; everyone has a smartphone now, Grandpa. People fly drones, clock hours into sex chat sessions, and use their phones as an extension of themselves. But above all else, there&#x27;s a clear lack of yakuza present.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Tojo isn&#x27;t really holding all that well together. Sugai sets flames to the city, attempting to take advantage of the declining organization to bookend Daigo&#x27;s reign. Someya, who literally works with him, insists on the world of yakuza shifting -- profit raises when you get rid of a lot of the silly conventions guys like Kiryu stand by. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;fatherhood&quot;&gt;Fatherhood!&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This series is about fatherhood. Nagoshi personally had an incredibly strong bond with his father and this encouraged the narrative of the original game to be the way it was, as well as allowing the theme to become the beating heart of the franchise. 6 explores the challenges of fatherhood in a quickly shifting world, and the need to sometimes break away from old conventions or change quickly in order to embrace those around you.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The core of 6&#x27;s conflicts pretty much originate from fatherly bonds in different ways. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kiryu&#x27;s relationship with Haruka.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yuta&#x27;s relationship with Haruto.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Big Lo (Saio Triad leader)&#x27;s relationship with Jimmy and Yuta. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hirose&#x27;s relationship with his boys, and Hirose&#x27;s relationship with Heizo Iwami.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kiryu and Daigo.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#x27;s... not subtle. Yuta&#x27;s entire arc as a character is being able to break the cycle of shitty upbringing to become a real father of his own. Despite being a &amp;quot;black child&amp;quot; -- kids that don&#x27;t fall under the one-child policy -- and treated like nothing but an asset to the Saio Triad, he&#x27;s able to take responsibility for his kid (after Kiryu punches him into shape). &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#x27;t think 6 could even work juggling both this subplot and also bringing in a bunch of older characters. They... wouldn&#x27;t really have any relevance or do anything meaningful. They&#x27;d just sit there.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this is an issue with games like Yakuza 5 and Lost Judgment, which have characters that have gone through full arcs in past appearances and now don&#x27;t really have anywhere to go outside of just becoming mouthpieces for their beliefs or very paper-thin single-purpose existences. No hate to either of those, I like them quite a bit and maybe even more than 6.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;6-is-not-a-betrayal-of-past-games&quot;&gt;6 is not a betrayal of past games&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it wasn&#x27;t obvious already, 6 has a lot of reverence for the rest of the series, especially Yakuza 3. One thing I think a lot of people misunderstand about these games is that Kiryu from the get go will never be able to leave behind conflict so long as he exists. In Yakuza 5, he insists on taking on a new identity, but realizes later on this can&#x27;t work. Haruka runs back to him, because she cares way more about her ojisan than an idol performance. She knows the risks and implications, and deals with them promptly in the next game. She&#x27;s willing to carry that weight, and so is he.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only way to ensure the people he loves stay safe is to unfortunately leave their lives. Kiryu, as a prolific member of a literal criminal organization, has a constant target on his head. Somebody will always look to him for conflict, even after the Tojo Clan dries up and dies. He chose to join this life all the way back at Himawari Orphanage, and there is no real way for him to pull out at this point. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;m sure this is unintentional, but I think the finality of 6&#x27;s ending and his departure from his family works well at poking fun at RGG&#x27;s insistence on bringing this guy back constantly. Yakuza 3 was supposed to be his last game, and maybe if things wrapped up then I could understand him taking the slow life and enjoying Okinawa. But they brought him back in 4. And... despite him not even wanting it, he&#x27;s back in 5. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;7-gaiden-and-8-we-have-to-let-kiryu-go&quot;&gt;7, Gaiden, and 8 -- we have to let Kiryu go.&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gonna catch a lot of flak for this, but I don&#x27;t really think anything Kiryu post-6 was necessary. Like, at all. His appearance in 7 is downright disrespectful towards his sacrifice before. I don&#x27;t care if it&#x27;s somewhat honored by the people around him, he shouldn&#x27;t be casually strolling around Yokohama like that.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gaiden is a really solid self-contained piece that works by course-correcting from Kiryu in 7 and helping tie things back into 6&#x27;s sacrifice.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;8... I can&#x27;t really make any solid statements on, but I do think one of my concerns is this being the glup shitto game that I&#x27;m happy 6 wasn&#x27;t. The game has completely abandoned the secrecy of Kiryu, which isn&#x27;t inherently a bad thing, but his story still needs to END.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The potential of Kiryu becoming unable to fight, either by dying or losing enough strength from his cancer, would provide a level of finality to his life, which is what I really need. I just don&#x27;t want to leave the game feeling like 6&#x27;s very bold sacrifice was in vain.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yakuza 6 is far from a perfect game, but I think I&#x27;ve highlighted why it&#x27;s at the very least an incredibly thoughtful and meaningful game that understands who Kiryu is and what this series stands for. It doesn&#x27;t deserve a black sheep status.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>How to fix Flatpak</title>
          <pubDate>Tue, 19 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Unknown</author>
          <link>https://zandyne.xyz/blog/flatpak/</link>
          <guid>https://zandyne.xyz/blog/flatpak/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://zandyne.xyz/blog/flatpak/">&lt;p&gt;Desktop Linux has a lot of potential to be a lot more robust and secure in the same vein as projects roughly based on it like GrapheneOS. The Steam Deck is a very popular device nowadays that happily chugs along running it. But there have to be some significant changes in the way the desktop paradigm is approached and how permissions and access work.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Flatpak is one piece of a puzzle, but I feel its sandboxing functionality is not only unhelpful, but potentially dangerous as it lulls users into a false sense of security.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-s-the-point-of-sandboxing-and-permissions&quot;&gt;What&#x27;s the point of sandboxing and permissions?&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a nutshell, functional sandboxing gives the user choice over how, when, and where applications are able to do anything. This is something that is fundamentally at odds with the way UNIX is designed, where the expectation was certain directories were far more crucial than a user&#x27;s home directory or configs. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reality is the vast majority of computers (mobile, cloud, server, desktop, IoT) are &lt;em&gt;single-user&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. There is one user that is assigned in each of your Kubernetes or Docker container, one user on your iPhone, and generally one or two users on a desktop computer or a laptop. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pretty much any meaningful data on an end-user&#x27;s computer is sitting in $HOME or C:\Users\username.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; length=&quot;100%&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;&#x2F;1337.webp&quot;&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Operating systems are easy to reinstall if broken, it&#x27;s not a big deal. But your precious Chun-Li goon pics are widely accessible in a single folder and anyone who wants access will be able to see them. I&#x27;m not just talking about physical access but all sorts of script kiddie tools to nab someone&#x27;s private info.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#x27;re someone working in an enterprise environment, IT, etc., you probably have some ssh keys lying around on your home folder. I&#x27;m almost certain they&#x27;re not gated behind some kind of security key or fingerprint scan -- anyone could easily just snatch them from you if given the chance.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;okay-but-what-is-flatpak-i-m-not-a-linux-user&quot;&gt;Okay, but what IS flatpak? I&#x27;m not a Linux user.&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Flatpak is an application distribution format that uses a lot of built-in Linux tech for isolation, sandboxing, and containerization. At its core, it&#x27;s a bunch of tooling built around bubblewrap, a sandboxing tool that doesn&#x27;t require root access. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ideally, application distribution becomes easier when developers now have to target only one runtime and one version of a package. It lightens the load off distro maintainers as they can leave the challenge of packaging all their software up to third-parties (like it&#x27;s done on literally every other platform).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Flatpak&#x27;s most widespread use currently is on the Steam Deck, as on the immutable read-only filesystem there is no way to invoke a system-level package manager. A lot of apps have migrated over to Flatpak: OBS Studio and Firefox being the most notable.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#x27;s absolutely crucial that a web browser is updated promptly and maintained well, and Mozilla&#x27;s &lt;em&gt;officially maintained&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; build of Firefox is a great way to ensure that. It avoid thes incredibly sloppy job that &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.debian.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;certain distros&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; have done trying to keep the most &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;cve.mitre.org&#x2F;cgi-bin&#x2F;cvename.cgi?name=CVE-2019-5847&quot;&gt;vulnerable&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and crucial part of a desktop user&#x27;s system safe.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, logically, the main thing you want to have granular control over is your home directory. Why should you give much of a shit if an application can access &#x2F;proc or see mostly default config files strewn throughout your filesystem? There&#x27;s little to nothing there worth protecting.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why is it, then, that a ton of Flatpaks ship with full home directory access and everything else turned off? Not only does this not prevent any meaningful attacks to a desktop user, but it hurts its ability to be an interoperable and well-integrated app on your system.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you install Flatpaks currently, they come with pre-baked permissions that aren&#x27;t really communicated well. Packagers have made assumptions in terms of what folders and resources applications can access, which is the exact opposite of how sandboxing on a desktop should work.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everything should be an explicit choice of the user, within reason. Why does Chromium ship with FULL home directory access?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; length=&quot;100%&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;&#x2F;chromium.png&quot;&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is solved through having a robust permissions model that happens on an OS level rather than opt-in on some applications.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#x27;ve ever used a Mac,&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;or an iPhone,&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;or an Android phone,&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;or a UWP app installed on Windows,&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;you have been enjoying some degree of a sandbox already. Applications have to ask for access to specific folders, system resources, keystrokes, webcam and mic, and the list goes on. If you install Tinder on Google Play, it asks you after starting the app for location access. If you share your photos, it also gives you the ability to only pass through and share the ones you like. This is handled through sane, OS-level prompts conveyed to the user in a more comprehensible way.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Computers are more complex than phones&amp;quot; you might be thinking, but the same concept still applies. Look no further than macOS enforcing this across the board and still having a healthy app ecosystem.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Linux servers have mandatory access control systems like SELinux and AppArmor that are a more sophisticated version of this concept, but they don&#x27;t really do much to help a desktop user. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having an OS-level sandbox (and using Linux&#x27;s existing tools like &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;flatpak.github.io&#x2F;xdg-desktop-portal&#x2F;&quot;&gt;portals&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; to grant the access) would not only make the sandboxing of tools like flatpak more reasonable (assuming it would integrated properly with flatpak), but also give a layer of protection to all sorts of other shit you install on your computer.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next step, I guess, would be binary signing libraries and applications, but that&#x27;s a whole &#x27;nother article.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Self-hosting content: why you should care, and how to start</title>
          <pubDate>Fri, 15 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Unknown</author>
          <link>https://zandyne.xyz/blog/selfhosting/</link>
          <guid>https://zandyne.xyz/blog/selfhosting/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://zandyne.xyz/blog/selfhosting/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Want to make clear that I&#x27;m new to this whole space, and will probably get some stuff wrong. If anything stands out as being inaccurate, don&#x27;t shy away from letting me know on any of my socials.&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ever use Netflix and just really enjoy a series? Maybe it wasn&#x27;t the greatest thing ever, and maybe you just watched it only once and liked it, but it stays in the back of your brain.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doesn&#x27;t it suck to realize when you go to look for it again that Netflix has decided for some reason you no longer deserve to have that content? Nothing you can do about it, and you&#x27;re throwing at least $7 a month at them. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a ton of examples of shit like this. The modern Internet and the select few services that control content nowadays for the majority of people are able to have a stranglehold on what you can see, when you can see it, and how. Using the wrong browser? Enjoy DRM blocking you from enjoying 4K video streaming, even though your hardware is fully capable. Paid for a movie or game or something? Who cares, it&#x27;ll be stripped away from you on a whim. Tech companies do not care, and do not have a vested interest in caring either.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thing is, it&#x27;s become easier and easier to fire up functional alternatives to a lot of ephemeral, subscription-based software or restrictive, walled garden content. The barrier to entry has never been lower. I&#x27;m gonna direct y&#x27;all to some very useful tools and let you run from there.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;jellyfin-and-plex&quot;&gt;Jellyfin and Plex&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Netflix just kinda... sucks? None of these streaming services offer particularly good user experience nowadays and there&#x27;s all sorts of frustrating limitations involved. You don&#x27;t &lt;em&gt;have&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; to tolerate it. There are functional alternatives that respect you as a user much more.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;plex&quot;&gt;Plex&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;plex.tv&quot;&gt;Plex&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; is better than the alternative of a Netflix or Disney+, but it&#x27;s somewhat locked down and has some frustrating limitations. However, it&#x27;s very mature and has been around for quite a while. This offers a lot of immediate advantages:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plex has official apps on a ton of devices, like consoles, smart TVs, and phones.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plex is more thoroughly documented.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plex&#x27;s UI is more polished. There are a handful of minor quirks you have to put up with on Jellyfin.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plex, however, is limited in terms of the kinds of hardware you can use for transcoding, and is a lot more resource intensive. It might not be the best choice if you&#x27;re someone on a weaker or older hardware.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;jellyfin&quot;&gt;Jellyfin&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;jellyfin.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Jellyfin&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; is an open-source fork of the older Emby media server. It&#x27;s very flexible, lightweight, and it&#x27;s what I personally use. It&#x27;s not quite as polished, but it works great on my AMD and Intel hardware.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Well, how do I set these up?&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Glad you asked. Both programs offer easy downloads for Windows, Linux, and macOS. You can always containerize Jellyfin, but that requires learning how to use Docker&#x2F;LXD&#x2F;Kubernetes tooling and that might not really make sense for your use case. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the program&#x27;s installed, see if you can set up your GPU to transcode and accelerate video. You can access Jellyfin&#x27;s web client on its default port, 8096, and Plex on 32400. From the machine you&#x27;re running the service on, just enter its IP followed by the port number. If you&#x27;re typing from the machine running the service, &amp;quot;localhost&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;127.0.0.1&amp;quot; will point to it. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These services are pretty self-explanatory and media organization is pretty easy. Your legally obtained Linux ISOs and homework is all organized neatly with chapter organization and subtitles and everything. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;music&quot;&gt;Music&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Music discovery is undeniably useful, but I&#x27;ve personally found that a large music library I&#x27;ve accumulated over time has allowed me to sit through more full albums. It&#x27;s nice to have control over everything and be able to hear all of the niche stuff that isn&#x27;t available on Spotify or Apple Music.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#x27;s a lot of self-hosted music services out there, just choose one. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;airsonic&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;airsonic.github.io&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Airsonic&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what I use. While it took a decent bit of time for it to properly cache and locate all of my music, once that was done it ran great. There are great clients on Android and iOS, a web client if you want that, and plenty of desktop clients.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;navidrome&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.navidrome.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Navidrome&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a newer option, and it&#x27;s a little rough around the edges. I wouldn&#x27;t recommend this unless you know how to spin up a Docker container (which, to be fair, isn&#x27;t the most difficult thing).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;pi-hole&quot;&gt;Pi-hole&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pi-hole.net&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Pi-hole&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; is a DNS sinkhole designed to be used on low-power hardware like a Raspberry Pi computer. It&#x27;s great for network-level blocking of ads, telemetry, and even entire domains. This can save tons of data, which is appealing on mobile devices, and generally makes the internet a little more usable and more lean. Pi-hole can run on pretty much anything. Personally, I&#x27;d recommend running this on its own dedicated device, or at least isolated from the other services running on it. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Honestly, you can get away with using a virtual machine for this, if you want an easy setup and don&#x27;t have another computer on hand that&#x27;s running Linux. Just make sure to use &lt;em&gt;bridged network&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; on the virtual machine so it has its own IP address exposed to your LAN. I recommend Debian or Ubuntu: you can install a desktop environment in the VM to make it easier and just run the one-liner here to set it up: &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;curl -sSL https:&#x2F;&#x2F;install.pi-hole.net | bash&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can use it as a full DHCP server, but for now, I&#x27;d recommend just going through the basic instrucitons on its site and using it as the default: a DNS server. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can set your router to use the Pi as its only DNS in its own settings, but you can also just add its IP in each of your devices&#x27; network configuration. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;static-ip&quot;&gt;Static IP&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#x27;re able to access your router&#x27;s settings, try to lease the computer running certain services a static IP. This will ensure that the DHCP server won&#x27;t decide to give it a different IP address in the future, ensuring that everything&#x27;s accessible.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#x27;re using Pi-hole, YOU MUST DO THIS for the device running the service.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;dns&quot;&gt;DNS&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Punching in an IP address every time you want to access your sites is a little inconvenient, so why not set things up with a dynamic DNS service and reverse proxying URLs. This video is perfectly functional and helpful and I&#x27;m going to link to it rather than type out basically identical instructions.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;textCenter&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe
        src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube-nocookie.com&#x2F;embed&#x2F;qlcVx-k-02E&quot;
        allow=&quot;accelerometer; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot;
        webkitallowfullscreen
        mozallowfullscreen
        allowfullscreen&gt;
    &lt;&#x2F;iframe&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You COULD just use Pi-hole for this. It&#x27;s up to you.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do I access these services away from home?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;tailscale&quot;&gt;Tailscale&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;tailscale.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Tailscale&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; is awesome, and it&#x27;s one of the first tools I recommend to people that want a secure method of accessing their shit from home. It&#x27;s really just a matter of installing the program on each device you&#x27;re interested in, and logging in when asked for credentials.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#x27;re connected to the Tailscale VPN, all of your services hosted from home are accessible. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make sure it&#x27;s installed on each device that you want accessible.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-about-wireguard-openvpn&quot;&gt;What about Wireguard&#x2F;OpenVPN?&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#x27;re asking that question, this guide probably isn&#x27;t for you... a simple WireGuard VPN to home is easier to set up and provides better bandwidth, but it requires you to expose a port. I personally use &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pivpn.io&#x2F;&quot;&gt;PiVPN&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and it works great, but Tailscale &amp;quot;just works&amp;quot; for most users. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;vps-aws-etc&quot;&gt;VPS, AWS, etc.&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Self-hosting&amp;quot; generally means... hosting your own content, but a VPS is like the next step removed from that. If you choose a good service, you can have a functional server in the cloud that can be accessed like anything else. On some networks (CGNAT), this might be the only way to have some control. A lot of the stuff I suggested works fine on a VPS you can rent out. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Owning the media you consume is a challenge, and requires more of a learning curve than just paying for a bunch of monthly subscriptions. However, what you get out of it is way more control and flexibility over how you consume content, when you want to, and where you want to. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>The importance of PCs as a hobby</title>
          <pubDate>Mon, 04 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Unknown</author>
          <link>https://zandyne.xyz/blog/pchobbyists/</link>
          <guid>https://zandyne.xyz/blog/pchobbyists/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://zandyne.xyz/blog/pchobbyists/">&lt;p&gt;If you asked me when I fell in love with personal computers, and why I was drawn into them as a kid so much, you&#x27;d be wrong if it was because I could be so much more productive. It wasn&#x27;t because of that. It wasn&#x27;t because I could pick up some new skills, learn a programming language, do something I could stick on a resume years later. I was a kid, and mentally I always will be in some ways.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What drew me into computers as a kid was the immense personalization and sense of ownership that came out of them. I loved being able to install tacky browser themes onto my browser, set fun wallpapers every day, and mess around with Flash games. That was a large chunk of my childhood, and while my PS2 was awesome and had all the games I could ever want, something about the late 2000s and early 2010s internet drew me in. Something about the idea that everyone around me on sites like Newgrounds was just a guy behind a keyboard was incredibly comforting.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were so many websites to visit, so much weird shit to do, and while all of it was ultimately just meandering about, who the fuck cares? My world had expanded quite a bit.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I got a little older, I got my first computer -- an ancient dual-core Pentium running Vista. I treated that thing amazingly, and it went through some crazy shit with me. I learned the ins and outs of Windows, played a ton of old Steam games like Half-Life, and messed around with crazy desktop enhancements like Rainmeter. As I had increasingly become a loser and lost friends in elementary and middle school, PCs were the main thing grounding me in an online community. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#x27;s only so much personalization you can do on Windows. The reality is that the UX paradigms are so traditional and unchanging for the amount of widespread use the operating system sees, that there&#x27;s only so much you can do to make it &amp;quot;yours&amp;quot; in a hobbyist sense.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One day, I installed Linux.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went to grab Ubuntu, thinking it was a good beginner&#x27;s option as most of the front-facing Internet seemed to mention it. I also had Linux Mint ready to install (and in retrospect it probably would have given me less issues), but I jumped straight on. But get this -- it wasn&#x27;t normal Ubuntu, which was rocking Unity at the time, it was the pared-down Openbox desktop version for low-end computers, aptly named Lubuntu. I think this crippled my immediate experience and enjoyment of desktop Linux as it felt like using Windows XP at points.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had a cheap Realtek USB Wi-Fi adapter I had been using on Windows and it predictably just would not work out of the box on a stripped down Ubuntu. So, I kinda gave up for a little bit.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then I happened to install &amp;quot;proper&amp;quot; Ubuntu -- 14.04 or 15.04? Anyways, it absolutely blew my mind. I hadn&#x27;t ever seen something designed like it before, and it was just so unique and interesting to mess around with. I tinkered the living shit out of it, installing icon themes, a fresh GTK theme, fonts, the whole kitchen sink. Absolutely nothing productive was getting done on that computer at that point, but it didn&#x27;t really matter. I finally felt like my computer was actually mine.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually, I obtained an old low-end Acer laptop, with abysmal battery life. Ended up throwing Ubuntu on that, too. Man, was that an awesome experience. Despite the shitty hardware, I learned quite a bit using that thing. I jumped from desktop to desktop, trying everything out there, until I finally landed on KDE Plasma, which blew my mind in terms of the sheer configurability. It wasn&#x27;t the most stable or robust at the time, but KDE has always been able to pride itself on being incredibly flexible. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I kept obtaining hand-me-down laptops and desktops for a while, enjoying Linux and getting incredibly familiar with it as a platform. My desktop obsession turned into a tiling window manager obsession, as I saw Cool People on my YouTube timeline showing off the wildest, most productive (allegedly) environments I&#x27;ve ever seen. It was nice just feeling part of a community that encouraged me to really own my own PC. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;this-isn-t-the-norm-and-that-sucks&quot;&gt;This isn&#x27;t the norm, and that sucks&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apple acolytes will insist that computers are an extension of themselves. While I think in concept they&#x27;re right, there&#x27;s a big difference between choosing the blueberry-colored iMac G3 because it fit your personality best and having a blast making it yours and buying a minimalist, utilitarian silver MacBook for work. Computers in general have become infinitely more accessible, functional, and affordable, but at the sacrifice of losing a lot of their toy-like elements that hobbyists enjoy. I&#x27;m not necessarily opposed to this entirely, but I&#x27;m scared to see a world where the personal computer just becomes a box that you turn on to run spreadsheet software and send emails. That&#x27;s what they are to most people in the office, and while I get sometimes shit just needs to get done, there&#x27;s no soul to any of that.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What the fuck happened?&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you look now, I&#x27;m typing this on a MacBook Air. At some point, there was a shift in my thinking and a willingness to lean into pragmatism. Obviously this is partly because I&#x27;m employed and have a family to feed and everything, but there are still large gaps in my day sometimes where I could absolutely do the same bullshit. Instead of gaming, I could absolutely mess around with a barebones Arch install and just go nuts. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;textCenter&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe
        src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube-nocookie.com&#x2F;embed&#x2F;WSh_X2laSDI&quot;
        allow=&quot;accelerometer; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot;
        webkitallowfullscreen
        mozallowfullscreen
        allowfullscreen&gt;
    &lt;&#x2F;iframe&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I want to later touch on the Internet specifically as a whole. I just think this kind of &amp;quot;awakening&amp;quot; I went through with desktop Linux was incredibly important in encouraging my later passion for it -- I would not have the drive to earn a handful of networking and Linux-related certs if it was just something I picked up for work. I think every kid that has even the tiniest bit of interest in technology needs to be sit down in front of an old ThinkPad or something and told to just go nuts unsupervised. MDM issued Chromebooks or Mom&#x27;s MacBook Pro are not the same -- I mean a huge inch and a half thick brick that struggles to pull 3 hours of battery. At least, that&#x27;s what I&#x27;d do.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please look at &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;old.reddit.com&#x2F;r&#x2F;unixporn&quot;&gt;unixporn&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; when you have the chance.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Why Scott Pilgrim Takes Off doesn&#x27;t work</title>
          <pubDate>Tue, 28 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Unknown</author>
          <link>https://zandyne.xyz/blog/scottpilgrimtakesoff/</link>
          <guid>https://zandyne.xyz/blog/scottpilgrimtakesoff/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://zandyne.xyz/blog/scottpilgrimtakesoff/">&lt;p&gt;I recently finished the recent Rebuild of Eva-type sequel series Scott Pilgrim Takes Off. I think I enjoyed my time with the first few episodes, but there seems to be a general fundamental lack of understanding of what made the original comics work.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-series-revolves-around-scott-and-does-not-work-when-he-is-not-there&quot;&gt;The series revolves around Scott and does not work when he is not there&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;ve seen people on Twitter smugly insist on Scott &amp;quot;being there&amp;quot; because the anime constantly references stuff he did and his presence there, or argue that the original comic exists. Neither of these takes make sense, though. The core of this franchise is Scott Pilgrim and his own personal growth. It&#x27;s about the way he&#x27;s able to reconcile with himself and work through his issues with Ramona.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;scott-doesn-t-face-any-consequences-for-his-mistakes&quot;&gt;Scott doesn&#x27;t face any consequences for his mistakes&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If y&#x27;all thought the movie let this kid off the hook, this is arguably worse. Most of the Bad Shit this guy does is brushed off and not even taken seriously. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knives is able to bounce back and is largely fine and able to get over her lingering feelings incredibly quickly and conveniently at a point where Scott returns without having to worry much about the conflict, and they spell out loud How Bad Dating a High Schooler Was, Who Knew. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compare this to the comic where Scott and Knives relapse, after she insists the guy is toxic and unhealthy for her but that she&#x27;s still trying to get over her feelings, and after kissing there&#x27;s just nothing but mutual disgust.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He has to live with and carry that weight, and it can&#x27;t just be forgotten as a footnote in his larger life.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Same thing with Envy... he just never resolves anything with her and she&#x27;s portrayed as strangely bitchy throughout the story, showing up to Scott&#x27;s &amp;quot;funeral&amp;quot; just to sing a snarky song. The thing about Envy is &lt;em&gt;Scott exaggerates how bad she is in his head and she&#x27;s not on the same level as Ramona&#x27;s evil exes.&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;crack-fic-energy&quot;&gt;Crack fic energy&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;What if&amp;quot; scenarios aren&#x27;t inherently bad. I think they can work if there&#x27;s a clear focus and direction behind their writing. However, there&#x27;s a certain point in the anime where the execution of the premise goes over a threshold and just becomes silly.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#x27;t think all of Ramona&#x27;s ex-es needed several episodes of fleshing out as realized characters. I&#x27;m not inherently against it, but I feel like with the increased focused on those characters, time that could be better spent exploring the core cast outside of Scott is lost.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#x27;s also jarring to have every single one of them sort out their problems and become completely rehabilitated people. I can&#x27;t help but feel it&#x27;s a bit idealistic to have them all sort out their issues in that way.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The implication from the comic has always been that Ramona is somewhat reasonable in having a pattern of running away from her relationships, as not all of them have been great experiences. I just don&#x27;t feel as if personally walking up to every single one of your shitty ex-boyfriends and talking things out is really a good idea.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It works with Scott as most of the people he&#x27;s dated have lives outside of him and aren&#x27;t really that much worse people than him. With Lisa, nothing ever actually kicked off, with Kim, they&#x27;re still pretty good friends, and with Envy, he&#x27;s able to get over his resentment. It doesn&#x27;t work the same way when Ramona has assholes like Gideon in her past.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think Roxie was actually handled pretty well and enjoyed the way she was written, but that didn&#x27;t warrant everybody else getting the same treatment.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-romance-does-not-work&quot;&gt;The romance does not work&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the reasons Ramona and Scott&#x27;s relationship was so compelling to me when I read the story years back was the fact that they were by no means some couple fated to just bond together and they (especially Scott) needed to put actual effort into the relationship for it to sustain itself. They work through each others&#x27; issues together.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Takes Off decides to just place Ramona in a space where she&#x27;s able to have a self-contained character arc without Scott helping her confront her issues. It misses how Scott challenges Ramona on her insistence to hide from her problems and run away, but clearly he just didn&#x27;t need to exist at all?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the end of the story, we&#x27;re greeted with a Scott Pilgrim that doesn&#x27;t actually go on a thorough journey of personal growth, and just naturally decides to be less of an asshole despite not actually learning anything. He doesn&#x27;t reconcile things with Envy, Lisa, or Kim.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ramona wants to save a guy she knew for like two days, not because he did anything particularly significant, but because they&#x27;re just cosmologically fated to be together in this timeline. It&#x27;s undeserved and I&#x27;m confused at how such a fundamental misunderstanding of what the comics have to say about healthy relationships is pushed here, even unintentionally.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mean, shit, he doesn&#x27;t even know her age by the end.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Ownership, technology, and convenience -- highlighting the issue through laptops</title>
          <pubDate>Sat, 04 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Unknown</author>
          <link>https://zandyne.xyz/blog/righttorepair/</link>
          <guid>https://zandyne.xyz/blog/righttorepair/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://zandyne.xyz/blog/righttorepair/">&lt;p&gt;We live in a world where ownership of technology seems to be stripped away every day. It&#x27;s not just being able to crack open your laptop and replace the storage, it&#x27;s as bad as physical games being in their sunset period due to a bunch of technical and profit-driven reasons. It&#x27;s really bad if you happen to be someone that is concerned with what they do and do NOT own in this current age. I don&#x27;t like this trend and think for the most part it&#x27;s anti-consumer.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;However, it&#x27;s important to understand that digital ownership and repairability are not something most consumers actually care about.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I get it. The reason most consumers do not care whether or not their MacBook has SODIMM slots for replaceable memory and an M.2 slot for storage is because that&#x27;s not something anyone does on a device they&#x27;ve spent more than a grand on. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;People use their computers as a tool for an end. People will buy obtuse, difficult to buy cars because they offer the features and value they&#x27;re looking for, and their work computer is no different.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#x27;s not even necessarily people that aren&#x27;t technically inclined. It needs to be made incredibly apparent that in a world where time is money, nobody wants to waste it on a computer. It makes a lot more sense to hand it over to a professional and have Genius Bar or the equivalent for the vendor they bought their computer from to figure it out. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mobile hardware (laptops, phones, and tablets) have all become less modular, less repairable, and frustratingly, more functional. They&#x27;re packed in smaller form factors with proprietary arrangements of components that might as well be a black box to normal consumers. Gone are the days of easily being able to pop off the back of your phone&#x27;s battery and slip in another -- replacing screens and battery can mean removing the waterproof seal off your phone and navigating through tiny, hard to track cables and pieces. In a world where no one outside of a small minority is repairing computers, and where hardware vendors have realized this fact and capitalized on it, what&#x27;s the best way to discourage waste and create a somewhat sustainable ecosystem for consumers? &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Robust recycling programs are what the industry SHOULD be pointing towards. Unfortunately, as much as Apple, Lenovo, Dell, and others pride themselves on being eco-friendly, they&#x27;re all notorious for wasting tons and tons of damaged hardware. &lt;strong&gt;This needs to be something strong-armed by the government -- sustainability is just too important.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Framework offers incredibly modular laptops at a premium, and it&#x27;s cool that there&#x27;s hardware out there that you can repair just like your modest Japanese car. Some people really, really want to be able to own and understand everything about the tools they need all day, and it&#x27;s understandable. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Repairable devices can be treated like an extension of your body -- you can have a well-oiled machine just like a a healthy body.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is Framework&#x27;s offerings &lt;em&gt;make no sense&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; to most people. Repairability is cool, but who cares about that when it ships with a pretty standard IPS panel, loud fans, weak battery life, little to no vertical integration in the same vein as a Dell XPS or MacBook, and a bunch of other caveats? It&#x27;s a cool novelty, but not something that actually makes sense for your average consumer.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;textCenter&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe
        src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube-nocookie.com&#x2F;embed&#x2F;km3MVZ8HZeY&quot;
        allow=&quot;accelerometer; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot;
        webkitallowfullscreen
        mozallowfullscreen
        allowfullscreen&gt;
    &lt;&#x2F;iframe&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Old ThinkPads are in the same camp here. This isn&#x27;t coming from a hater, most of my history with laptops consists of Reddit golden child ThinkPads from yesteryear, fitted with RAM and screen upgrades, Wi-Fi chip replacements, and everything in between.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The T430 is widely loved because despite its bulky build, &lt;em&gt;almost everything on the device can be repaired or replaced.&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;*
Let&#x27;s take a look:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Socketed CPU&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two DDR3 DIMM slots&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easy to access SATA port&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MSATA port in the back&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can support a classic 7-row keyboard&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can support a 1080p display mod&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MASSIVE 92Wh battery upgrade, plus very rare slice battery for another 100 or so&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can get a pretty solid laptop from 2013 to maybe... 2018 if you upgrade everything here. It&#x27;s a heavy, massive brick that thermal throttles, doesn&#x27;t support modern video codecs like VP9 or AV1 (have fun on YouTube and most of the modern web), and subpar 6 hour or less battery life even with that massive ass battery. It&#x27;s incredibly fucking cool how it reaches PC-level upgradeability, but genuinely who cares? I have literally owned one and got through my first year of college with an upgraded T430 like this, so I&#x27;m speaking from experience.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#x27;s no HDMI, no USB-C&#x2F;Thunderbolt, only two USB 3 ports, mini-DP and VGA. It&#x27;s packed with a ton of obsolete ports.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;textCenter&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe
        src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube-nocookie.com&#x2F;embed&#x2F;r2v-Y8CdE1w&quot;
        allow=&quot;accelerometer; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot;
        webkitallowfullscreen
        mozallowfullscreen
        allowfullscreen&gt;
    &lt;&#x2F;iframe&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, but what about something more modern? A T480, perhaps?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The T480 actually isn&#x27;t too bad of an older laptop. I&#x27;ve used one for a decent amount of time and it&#x27;s currently a daily driver while I wait to get a newer MacBook for myself. Let&#x27;s look at its upgradability:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two DDR4 slots&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SATA slot with M.2 adapter&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;WWAN M.2 slot that can fit another SSD&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Low-power 1080p, 1440p and 4k display upgrades&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dual-pipe heatsink mod for better cooling on Nvidia-less models&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Big 72Wh external battery to be paired with the internal 24Wh one&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#x27;s got two Thunderbolt 3 ports, solid build quality, and everything seems pretty appealing. You get a more pragmatic configurable laptop, and it might be a great daily driver for your Linux distro of choice or a Windows install. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what&#x27;s the problem? The severe thermal throttling (see a pattern?). Intel laptops have gotten worse and worse about this. The fans ramp up almost immediately if you even charge the damn thing, not to mention doing any kind of mildly intensive work. Aggressive undervolts are needed to not have an unbearably loud, hot computer.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The T480 style of more fresh, modern repairability seems incredibly awesome, but it&#x27;s a real challenge to have an experience on par with what consumers expect nowadays.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modern ThinkPads are often fitted with much more efficient Ryzen CPUs, and sip away at power quietly in comparison. While Lenovo&#x27;s build quality has fallen off, they&#x27;re still generally a better investment if you&#x27;re the average consumer that values certain things more than being able to hypothetically upgrade their laptop.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The approach that works better for most consumers is buying all the hardware they need AT purchase and sticking with that machine until it gets old. It works for phones, and so laptops are literally no different in this regard. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;apple-silicon-is-the-ultimate-spit-in-the-face-to-the-entire-hobbyist-repairable-laptop-space&quot;&gt;Apple Silicon is the ultimate spit in the face to the entire hobbyist repairable laptop space.&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;textCenter&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe
        src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube-nocookie.com&#x2F;embed&#x2F;N9bVlpMtSv4&quot;
        allow=&quot;accelerometer; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot;
        webkitallowfullscreen
        mozallowfullscreen
        allowfullscreen&gt;
    &lt;&#x2F;iframe&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#x27;s incredibly frustrating knowing the reality is hyper-efficient, proprietary SoCs blow the entire laptop industry out of the water and have made everything else look silly. When you can squeeze 18-20 hours of battery life off current-gen offerings from Apple, when the integrated, unified, and impossible to replace memory and storage offer performance benefits, you start to realize that the tradeoff of it becoming a complete black box for consumers just does not matter. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#x27;s not even that these kinds of proprietary components have to be entirely locked down -- Apple could easily introduce an ecosystem of proprietary modular components. They just don&#x27;t care, and they KNOW their audience doesn&#x27;t either. It&#x27;s a smug &amp;quot;fuck you&amp;quot; that would only come from this company being on top for once after shipping garbage laptops from like 2016 all the way to 2019.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apple will try to skirt around their general locked-down nature with half-assed programs like their self-service repair shit, but at the end of the day they know their customers are NOT opening up their computers. And honestly, neither am I.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Praying for a world where we can strike a better balance between convenience, repairability, and environmental sustainability.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;M.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>How do we &#x27;fix&#x27; the Linux desktop?</title>
          <pubDate>Fri, 20 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Unknown</author>
          <link>https://zandyne.xyz/blog/linuxdesktop/</link>
          <guid>https://zandyne.xyz/blog/linuxdesktop/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://zandyne.xyz/blog/linuxdesktop/">&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, Linux desktops leverage technologies that aren&#x27;t sustainable if it&#x27;s going to see widespread use on modern computers and be issued out as a preinstalled product on them. I&#x27;m going to bring up examples of several other modern operating systems used on the desktop to show that there is a better, more robust design model that makes sense for &amp;quot;normies&amp;quot;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;separation-between-system-and-user&quot;&gt;Separation between &lt;em&gt;system&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;user&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is very obviously a point influenced by macOS, but it still reigns true. There&#x27;s no Linux System to target on the desktop, or at least there isn&#x27;t with the traditional distribution model. Two people&#x27;s Ubuntu installations can vary wildly differently, and there&#x27;s no consistent &amp;quot;system&amp;quot; it an rely on and deploy on modern computers. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dell offers XPS laptops shipped with Ubuntu, and other vendors have shipped out Ubuntu, Fedora, and even Manjaro on their laptops. But here&#x27;s the question: how do you do tech support and help troubleshoot issues on their laptops when they&#x27;re all heavily customized with tons of packages straying from the default? What do you even deploy to these laptops and desktop systems besides some custom-built Dell XPS Ubuntu ISO that they have to maintain on their own terms?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having a system (volume) also allows you to sign all binaries part of that system. Since macOS 11, Apple has deployed &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;support.apple.com&#x2F;guide&#x2F;mac-help&#x2F;what-is-a-signed-system-volume-mchl0f9af76f&#x2F;mac&quot;&gt;signed system volumes&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; that limits access to files on the system and refuses to allow binaries without a valid cryptographic signature. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outside of the obvious security benefits of this approach, it offers the ability to keep past OS installations as &lt;em&gt;volumes&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, which can have their own snapshots used with Time Machine (Mac&#x27;s user-facing OS backup app).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;windows&quot;&gt;Windows&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Uh, Windows is a mess and while there&#x27;s some level of separation involved where your average program will not bring the entire computer down, there&#x27;s not really a guarantee. Tons of Windows installations have gross registry hacks or tweaks or whatever and there&#x27;s not really much consistency between installations, either. Most vendors ship out their own custom images of Windows, and you can do it somewhat easily with DISM, but it&#x27;s ultimately a hack over a really janky system. It&#x27;s still slightly better than the complete lack of separation we have on Linux:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;can-t-we-do-this-in-linux&quot;&gt;Can&#x27;t we do this in Linux?&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Linux has some of this tech already, and has for a while. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fedora Silverblue offers image-based updates that issue out system updates through Git-like library management called ostree. This model is the closest we&#x27;ve gotten to some kind of &amp;quot;system&amp;quot; on a desktop Linux system. You have your desktop environment, basic applications like a terminal or a text editor, graphics drivers, kernel, etc. all as one easily reproducible system, rather than being a mishmash of different packages pull from repositories. This is great. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can&#x27;t write to Silverblue&#x27;s filesystem, outside of &#x2F;etc, which it keeps track of file changes with, and some other directories like &#x2F;var&#x2F;home (which is used as the &#x2F;home directory) and &#x2F;tmp. This makes it not only newcomer proof but a reliable solution for even experienced Linux users that aren&#x27;t interested in babysitting their distro. It makes everything easier to troubleshoot and fix for distro maintainers.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The logic with Silverblue and similar systems is using Flatpak, a sandboxed and containerized application format, for installing most software. This keeps the base system neat, tidy, and isolated while package maintainers can deploy their own applications, and there&#x27;s no risk of the two interfering or causing package conflicts. It also makes it way easier to debug problems with both.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a project called &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;universal-blue.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Universal Blue&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, which already takes advantage of the technologies behind Silverblue to offer various customized images for different use cases. As you can see, there&#x27;s still plenty of customization potential here, but it&#x27;s now done &lt;em&gt;declaratively&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;before&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; you install your system and not afterwards. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both ostree and flatpak still have deduplication, so there aren&#x27;t as many duplicate libraries hogging up space as you might expect. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;chromeos&quot;&gt;ChromeOS&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chromebooks, if you didn&#x27;t know, utilize this same image-based update system. The difference is compared to a Mac or a normal immutable Linux distro, CBs are very much so locked down and sandboxed from the top down. The expectation is you&#x27;re never really interacting with the system&#x27;s innards, because most work done on a Chromebook is using web applications and software and files in the cloud. However, notice how it&#x27;s not particularly difficult to support a Chromebook and solve software issues -- you can always &amp;quot;powerwash&amp;quot; and reset the device to its initial state and have a robust, reliable system there.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;steamos-3&quot;&gt;SteamOS 3&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Steam Deck is probably the best example of &amp;quot;traditional&amp;quot; Desktop Linux utilizing an immutable filesystem. You can tinker to your heart&#x27;s content on Deck, mucking around with mods and installing all sorts of weird games, without ever being concerned that the machine won&#x27;t boot tomorrow morning. Valve deploys ChromeOS-style updates and can ship them out without walking its users through the process of &lt;code&gt;pacman -Syu&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; and reading the Arch Linux news every time they want to update their computer. Most gamers will be fine with the offerings of Flatpaks available on Deck, and may not even know what a Flatpak is, just that Chrome and an Epic Games launcher and Dolphin Emulator are right there and easy to download.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The reality is that no end user should ever have to interface directly with a package manager. They shouldn&#x27;t even know what that is.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What the hell do I mean by this? Think about it this way -- People that use their computers as tools rather than wanting to understand how everything really works just want to be able to access the apps they need. They want Excel or Word or Zoom or Chrome or whatever, and the details in terms of how it&#x27;s obtained do not really matter.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you tell a newcomer to run &lt;code&gt;sudo apt install X&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; because it&#x27;s more reliable than using a GUI tool, you&#x27;ve already lost the plot.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Package managers should not be a user-facing tool, and their functions should be abstracted by &amp;quot;app stores&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;system updates&amp;quot;. If you&#x27;re a developer or someone that relies on a package manager, then you can easily fire up a container of some sort and go nuts. But Grandma does not need to know what&#x27;s happening behind the scenes.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember Linus Sebastian tried to install Steam on Pop!_OS and when he couldn&#x27;t get a basic app used for gaming working, he jumped to the terminal as per System76&#x27;s recommendations ON THEIR SITE?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pop, a distribution based on Debian, ended up with a package conflict between Steam and core system packages like the literal desktop environment and systemd. Not going to attack the distro maintainers, stuff happens, but HOW THE HELL IS THIS SOMETHING THAT CAN HAPPEN on a system marketed towards desktop users?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The traditional model for application distribution on Linux is just too brittle, and not particularly robust, reproducible, or safe. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And I think the issue is, a large amount of Linux users are incredibly stubborn in keeping the operating system this way.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are so many oldheads that will defend to the death the ability to literally remove your boot loader and kernel because you installed the wrong version of Chrome. To them, taking inspiration from other operating systems is the death of what they deem a better approach to computer usage.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I get it. Macs, Windows machines, phones, everything presents proprietary walled gardens designed to fuck over its users at points. There&#x27;s a certain level of reluctance here. But we&#x27;re not going to get anywhere if we don&#x27;t acknowledge the faults of desktop Linux.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-driver-situation&quot;&gt;The driver situation&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fundamentally, Linux has an issue with the way out-of-tree drivers are approached; while trying to integrate everything directly into the kernel and not having a stable ABI for them speeds up development and might make things immediately easier for kernel development, it&#x27;s an utterly impractical and unsustainable way to deal with the reality of the way drivers are managed. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DKMS is clunky and forces modules to be recompiled every time they&#x27;re used, and no out of tree drivers like ZFS, Nvidia, Broadcom, etc. integrate well when you need to do that every time. The reality is that a TON of people have older peripherals or just peripherals or devices that might have spotty Linux support or only target old versions of the kernel, and there&#x27;s no way to seamlessly have them integrate with a simple driver download in the same vein as Windows.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;macOS isn&#x27;t really that much better, as they&#x27;ve entirely ditched kernel extensions in favor of &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;support.apple.com&#x2F;guide&#x2F;deployment&#x2F;system-and-kernel-extensions-in-macos-depa5fb8376f&#x2F;web&quot;&gt;system extensions&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; or whatever, which run in userspace. I think Windows is kinda unbeat in this way as you can pretty much get any device or driver working regardless of age. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-can-we-do&quot;&gt;What can we do?&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, the driver situation is unlikely to improve anytime soon, it&#x27;s just a fundamental flaw for desktop usage for things to be arranged that way. One way to patch the flaws up here is to just keep integrating more and more drivers into the Linux kernel, so there&#x27;s no need to even bother with hacky solutions trying to integrate them. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, a robust image-based system can also ship with needed kernel modules, including out of tree ones, making for a more appealing proposition for hardware vendors to ship their custom-built version of a Linux distro. I can absolutely see a world where Dell ships out their own immutable distro with certain preinstalled tweaks or packages.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this comes from love and appreciation of Linux. I still daily drive it for large amounts of my day, and do ALL of my gaming and most programming, development, automation, machine learning, and a bunch of other stuff on a Linux desktop. I&#x27;m just tired of these long-standing issues and would like more people to embrace the future.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>I want shorter games with worse graphics</title>
          <pubDate>Thu, 19 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Unknown</author>
          <link>https://zandyne.xyz/blog/shortergames/</link>
          <guid>https://zandyne.xyz/blog/shortergames/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://zandyne.xyz/blog/shortergames/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;&#x2F;sonic.png&quot; alt=&quot;the sonic meme&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The triple-A game industry has gotten to the point of being absurdly, unsustainably bloated. Here are some of the reasons why, in my opinion, Shorter Games may actually be the right creative direction for the industry to take as a whole.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;development-cycles-can-reach-5-7-years-at-this-point-meaning-any-large-sprawling-project-can-be-an-enormous-risk&quot;&gt;Development cycles can reach 5-7 years at this point, meaning any large, sprawling project can be an enormous risk.&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While some developers make use of that big ass time window (see &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;store.steampowered.com&#x2F;app&#x2F;1086940&#x2F;Baldurs_Gate_3&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Baldur&#x27;s Gate 3&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;), in reality this means a lot more Starfields. When you&#x27;re taking enormous risks in terms of financing and development huge games, and publishers have to meet certain quotas, there&#x27;s less and less room for video games that target limited audiences. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;but-longer-time-means-more-quality&quot;&gt;But... longer time means more quality!&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In ideal circumstances, &lt;em&gt;holy shit&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; this is absolutely true. I&#x27;m not fundamentally against long development cycles and giving a project plenty of time to brew if it&#x27;s actually used properly, but for every passion project from an indie studio there&#x27;s false promises.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-longer-a-game-takes-to-release-the-more-out-of-touch-it-is-with-the-current-state-of-development&quot;&gt;The longer a game takes to release, the more &amp;quot;out of touch&amp;quot; it is with the current state of development.&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plenty of games releasing in 2023 are rocking old engines or technology, but outside of old tech, this can be as simple as a game with political commentary shipping out dated or having dialogue that belongs in 2018. My point is, the longer a game takes to ship out, and the longer it stays insulated as a project stewing, the more it ages. This means it&#x27;s a lot harder to push the envelope of innovation.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be fair, at the same time, constant innovation and pushing new engines and graphics technologies generally makes games harder to run and less accessible for a portion of gamers.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;it-needs-to-be-made-incredibly-clear-that-many-many-studios-nowadays-are-struggling&quot;&gt;It needs to be made incredibly clear that many, MANY studios nowadays are struggling.&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A large amount of studios burn money like a teenage girl at the mall, between marketing, salaries, and a ton of other expenses.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you&#x27;re barely above the red, ANYTHING will help you continue going. Even if your game developed in the last 5 years is not ready, shipping SOMETHING out during that time means money&#x27;s brought in. We live in an era where software and game patches can be done incredibly efficiently and quickly. When severely over-scoped video games need funding to stay in the green, what better way to get funds to feed your developers than to drop a shoddy release and scrape together funds from the poor souls willing to buy it?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cyberpunk&#x27;s a great example of a game forced to crumble under the weight of a studio aiming for an incredibly large scale project, and not delivering at launch. Nowadays, with the Phantom Liberty DLC, it&#x27;s viewed by most as a very solid RPG, but it took them a damn long time to reach that point. I&#x27;m all for innovation and pushing boundaries, but the scale in which so many games release is plain unsustainable and incredibly difficult to do in this current climate.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-about-the-worse-graphics-part&quot;&gt;What about the &amp;quot;worse graphics&amp;quot; part?&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#x27;t agree with it at all and think this point is silly. Video games should look good and push the envelope of what&#x27;s possible visually. I do think there are plenty of bland-looking hyper-realistic games out nowadays, but there&#x27;s nothing inherently wrong with realism and there&#x27;s plenty of degrees of separation between indie pixel art or cel-shaded game and the latest nice-looking UE5 game.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You all knew this, but what matters more in a video game is solid art direction. Cohesive visual design tied with graphical advancements create incredible products, and it&#x27;s a lot easier to do BOTH when your game is smaller in scale. &lt;em&gt;It&#x27;s also generally easier to optimize a game with less assets and moving parts to worry about.&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;easily-accessible-upscaling-tech-exists-and-is-more-and-more-prevalent&quot;&gt;Easily accessible upscaling tech exists and is more and more prevalent&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PC gamers have been given the ability to use Nvidia&#x27;s Deep Learning Super Sampling and AMD&#x27;s FidelityFX Super Resolution for a little while now, offering algorithms to run intensive games at lower resolutions scaled up to their display&#x27;s. This opens the door for a lot of taxing games to run on older hardware. The Steam Deck is a great example of a device that can use FSR to run powerful games. Even the struggling tablet hardware on the Nintendo Switch takes advantage of FSR to run games like Tears of the Kingdom at acceptable performance.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-industry-will-not-correct-itself-unless-gamers-decide-to-change&quot;&gt;The industry will not correct itself, unless gamers decide to change&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Long development cycles and expansive, sprawling video games may become the new norm, but they are absolutely NOT something that we can adjust to. Notice how the PS5 is about 5 years old and is just now seeing any semblance of games designed specifically to run on it. Plenty of PS4 games just never really finished development as its younger sibling came out, and most consoles ultimately have a lifespan of about 7 years. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;so-what-can-we-do&quot;&gt;So, what can we do?&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Off the bat, support indie developers. They kinda just do their own thing and it seems to work pretty well. There&#x27;s a lot of quality content coming out of that sphere, but these guys also need to put food on the table. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consumer activism is generally not a very effective strategy, unfortunately. I think that as a whole, the industry and its development trends will see a dramatic shift as gamers begin to get tired of open world formulas in video games. Ideally, they&#x27;d become an ambitious exception, rather than the norm that everyone defaults to.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;M.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Cyberbullying sucks, actually</title>
          <pubDate>Mon, 16 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Unknown</author>
          <link>https://zandyne.xyz/blog/cyberbullying/</link>
          <guid>https://zandyne.xyz/blog/cyberbullying/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://zandyne.xyz/blog/cyberbullying/">&lt;p&gt;Nothing I&#x27;m saying here should be controversial.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;m just baffled at how a lot of people have bought into the idea that cyberbullying is a simple thing people can just block out.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You need to understand that people cannot just ditch their social life online, especially if they &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;zandyne.xyz&#x2F;blog&#x2F;pipeline&#x2F;&quot;&gt;obtain validation&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; from it. Just like it&#x27;s hard to break off a friend group that might treat you like shit in real life, because you don&#x27;t really have any other options, it&#x27;s also really hard to break away from a community you&#x27;ve joined and become comfortable with on Discord or something.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you have some friends that you&#x27;re totally cool with in the same space as their friends that make you want to die, you&#x27;re kinda limited in options. You could maybe form a space without the people that make you uncomfortable, but that&#x27;s a great way to start drama. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe you start a group DM, but then someone decides to leak screenshots of you talking shit about the people you don&#x27;t like. Maybe it&#x27;s moving to a different platform altogether -- from Discord to Telegram or Twitter circles or some shit. I don&#x27;t know, my point is it&#x27;s not always very easy to just up and move and place yourself in a comfortable space where you STILL have some level of online socialization.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, no, I&#x27;m not saying that online communities are a replacement for offline frined groups. What I am saying is that a lot of people have a real desire for both, and feeling somewhat comfortable in both spaces is crucial to mental health. Disregarding this because online interactions &amp;quot;aren&#x27;t real&amp;quot; or something is a really limited view of the situation. Platforms like Discord allow for some level of anonymity, letting a lot of people comfortably interact with friends around them without feeling like they need to present a certain way. Voice training doesn&#x27;t matter on Discord unless you open voice chat, and no one&#x27;s going to judge whether you &amp;quot;pass&amp;quot; or not.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When people are blamed for taking drastic actions -- like self-harm or worse -- from cyberbullying, it&#x27;s not something we should downplay as being as simple as &amp;quot;turn off the computer&amp;quot;. Honestly, a lot of the time, that makes things worse as an entire angle of socialization may now have disappeared for someone.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you go to a Christian school or a heavily Christian workplace and come home to Christian family or friends, knowing damn well that they wouldn&#x27;t approve of you being gay, what space do you have but the Discord server you have with friends that lets you shoot the shit and say what&#x27;s on your mind? Would you really give up that space because one or two people push your buttons?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Why I kinda like Macs</title>
          <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Unknown</author>
          <link>https://zandyne.xyz/blog/macos/</link>
          <guid>https://zandyne.xyz/blog/macos/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://zandyne.xyz/blog/macos/">&lt;p&gt;So I&#x27;ve recently ended up using a lot of Macs due to work. Not just MacBooks, but iMacs. They range from current gen M1s and M2s to ancient 2012 MacBooks. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And... I have to say, I quite like the experience.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&#x27;t get me wrong, in terms of usability and functionality, I think Linux is leagues ahead. But GOD this is a way more usable experience than Windows, to the point where I&#x27;m seriously considering giving it a shot as a dual boot via GPU passthrough on my Linux PC.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;ll get into my issues with Windows later, but right now, I just want to highlight a lot of the things I like about Macs, on both the hardware and software front.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;hardware&quot;&gt;Hardware&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Macs all have a nice aluminum finish to them that makes them feel very premium and high-profile. The metal finish doesn&#x27;t inspire confidence that I&#x27;d be able to drop it from a flight of stairs though, but that&#x27;s most laptops that aren&#x27;t old ThinkPads or rugged military laptops. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The keyboards nowadays are quite good. They&#x27;re, again, not as good as a ThinkPad keyboard, and lack the incredibly useful trackpoint, but there are so many other advantages that it doesn&#x27;t really matter to me. I personally prefer keyboards with a bit more travel, but at minimum it&#x27;s a huge improvement from the weird feel and travel of the older Intel MacBooks in that weird phase.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apple Silicon is a really hard truth to accept, as someone that cares quite a bit about repairability and openness in hardware. There&#x27;s no real way to upgrade storage or RAM on Apple Silicon SoCs. This means once your M1 Mac becomes old and obsolete, there&#x27;s not much you can do if you didn&#x27;t spend the premium on more RAM and storage. The trade off, of course, is improved speed, but I&#x27;m not sure if it&#x27;s a worthy sacrifice.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The battery life and performance is absolutely absurd on these machines nowadays, so while it feels disgusting and sinful to me, the usability of these laptops ramps up incredibly well. At home, I have a bulky full ATX tower eating up space and making noise in my room. It&#x27;s not the loudest thing ever. It&#x27;s got a Noctua air cooler and Arctic PST PWM cast fans (which are a bit annoying). But, M1&#x2F;M2 Macs are &lt;em&gt;silent&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. I can go to bed and not hear a single thing, and that&#x27;s nice. They can fit into a smaller form factor and be passively cooled, which makes me dream of the day I can rest a mini-sized PC on my desk with performance on par with my current gaming PC.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;software&quot;&gt;Software&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think there are some things that are incredibly well thought-out about macOS. One of the things I actually really love is the difference in approach to keyboard shortcuts. On Windows and Linux, you have to memorize a bunch of unintuitive keyboard shortcuts revolving around the Super&#x2F;Meta&#x2F;Windows key. They&#x27;re not consistent or intuitive, in my opinion. The other day, in fact, I was working on a Windows machine when it prompted me to input CTRL+ALT+Delete in order to change the soon-to-expire password as per organization group policy. Kinda had to take a step back and realize &amp;quot;what the hell?&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the things I love is how reliable the C and V shortcuts are on Mac. Makes copy-pasting into terminals a dream, since you no longer have to awkwardly hit Shift+Ctrl+C or Shift+Ctrl+V to interact with content on the terminal. It&#x27;s the little things that count.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;macOS has had large chunks of its filesystem read-only since Catalina, and that&#x27;s also a really good choice, in my opinion. I&#x27;m a huge fan of immutable operating systems and think they offer benefits to stability and possibly even security. Apple issues out image-based updates in the same vein as iOS, Android, Chrome OS, and most immutable Linux distros, and I think this is the right call rather than the clunky experience that Windows and mutable Linux distros offer a lot of the time.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;textCenter&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe
        src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube-nocookie.com&#x2F;embed&#x2F;0506yDSgU7M&quot;
        allow=&quot;accelerometer; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot;
        webkitallowfullscreen
        mozallowfullscreen
        allowfullscreen&gt;
    &lt;&#x2F;iframe&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#x27;s no reason this should ever happen.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Software installation (that&#x27;s not done through the App Store itself) is as dead simple as dragging and dropping an application folder to the &lt;code&gt;&#x2F;Applications&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; folder. Most installers will prompt you for this automatically. It&#x27;s really straightforward and is a punch above the garbage .MSI installers on Windows. Unfortunately, not having a well-integrated first-party package manager sucks and makes installing a lot of software not as seamless as Linux.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brew works fine until you realize a huge chunk of software needs to be compiled. It&#x27;s kind of like FreeBSD ports or the AUR where a lot of stuff is available but it all needs to be compiled. Updates and installation can take &lt;em&gt;forever&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But most large, mainstream desktop apps are a simple as mounting a .DMG file and dragging&#x2F;dropping.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The window management is quite good in some areas, but lacking in others. The virtual desktop management is really solid, with a focus on neatly organizing full-screen apps. A three-finger swipe up on the trackpad gives me easy access to all of my desktops and windows, and a swipe to the left or right seamlessly switches them. Ctrl + arrow keys has the same behavior.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the window tiling features are so behind everything else it&#x27;s pathetic. It&#x27;s such a pain getting windows to tile properly, as you have to press and hold the maximize button to even do it. I don&#x27;t understand why this feature is so hard to access and why it&#x27;s so limited. You can install extensions to make this experience a little better, but it&#x27;s really embarrassing how insulated Apple can be at times.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Music production and any audio stuff has been incredibly solid on a Mac. I don&#x27;t really have any complaints, but I&#x27;ve found that I rarely run into compatibility issues with audio on any of the three operating systems I use for it. My MIDI controllers like my drum pad and keyboard work fine, but they work fine on everything. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Video editing has been fine, too. The experience is better than Linux in that regard as DaVinci Resolve is more stable and performant on AMD there. I&#x27;ve used it on my Hackintosh VM without any issues.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another big thing is how gorgeous the entire operating system looks. There&#x27;s a level of visual consistency that&#x27;s just completely absent of Windows, and that Linux is only just now working towards. One of my biggest issues with Windows in general is how ugly and incoherent everything looks as a whole. Every application does its own thing, and even built-in stuff can range from Windows 3.1 to XP to 10 to 11 in terms of UI style. It really irks me.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lack of any kind of gaming support is kind of preventing me from even considering trying this thing full-time. I do 100% of my gaming on Linux nowadays, between my PCs and my Steam Deck. I just game on the host system nowadays and it works fine, though.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-s-my-beef-with-windows-and-why-have-i-somewhat-come-around-to-apple-recently&quot;&gt;What&#x27;s my beef with Windows, and why have I somewhat come around to Apple recently?&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Windows, to me, represents the stuffy, old Oxford button-down shirt approach to desktop use. It&#x27;s not necessarily more efficient, it&#x27;s just familiar, and so bogged down in its familiarity that it brings everything else down with it. So many Linux distros aim to emulate Windows and all of its frustrating quirks, and they have a lot of the same usability issues as a result. There&#x27;s an insane focus on backwards compatibility and clinging to the old and familiar, and a lot of Windows use in general seems skewed towards old design conventions and legacy software. It feels &lt;em&gt;old&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, and not in a good and comfy way. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#x27;s far from being unusable, especially with Windows Subsystem for Linux and the wide berth of software support. Don&#x27;t get me wrong. I just really, &lt;em&gt;really&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; dislike using it nowadays. It feels unpolished. macOS, for better or worse, makes a lot of choices that distinguish it from Windows, and it&#x27;s not as much of a Swiss-army knife as Windows is as a result. It&#x27;s not your best option for video games, or CAD software, or a long list of other use cases. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;apple-sucks&quot;&gt;Apple sucks&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#x27;t love or even like Apple as a company. They provide proprietary, walled-garden products and entrap you in their ecosystem, without offering the flexibility that one might want integrating their products with non-Apple stuff. Good luck having solid integration between a Mac and an Android, or an iPhone and Linux. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They charge extravagant prices for their hardware and have a spotty track record that&#x27;s only now kind of bouncing back to where it was.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite this, I think macOS has become a pretty usable product for personal desktop use. If you need some specific legacy software, sure, go ahead and use Windows. If you need Samba shares, USE WINDOWS, PLEASE. If you need a more integrated development environment, or if you don&#x27;t want to lose out on flexibility, feel free to use desktop Linux. But honestly, for the most part, this shit &amp;quot;just works.&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;M.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>My thoughts on the Steam Deck</title>
          <pubDate>Fri, 06 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Unknown</author>
          <link>https://zandyne.xyz/blog/steamdeck/</link>
          <guid>https://zandyne.xyz/blog/steamdeck/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://zandyne.xyz/blog/steamdeck/">&lt;p&gt;The Steam Deck is Valve&#x27;s newest piece of tech, built on a &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.gamingonlinux.com&#x2F;2018&#x2F;09&#x2F;an-interview-with-the-developer-of-dxvk-part-of-what-makes-valves-steam-play-tick&#x2F;&quot;&gt;long history&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; of open source technology.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;winehq.org&quot;&gt;WINE&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; is a long-running project with the goal of translating Windows&#x27; Win32 API calls into something that Linux and macOS can run. It&#x27;s not emulation -- think about Firefox and Chrome. Chrome is what most of the web is designed for, but Firefox is its own implementation that can also browse the web.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#x27;s a video from Glorious Eggroll, a contributor to Linux gaming: &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;youtu.be&#x2F;K9khdYpMI5s&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;youtu.be&#x2F;K9khdYpMI5s&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Linux machines nowadays are able to also translated DirectX graphics calls to Vulkan or OpenGL, the former giving really, really solid performance and sometimes being outright more stable than the game running on Windows. Tons of money being thrown at these projects by Valve alongside a robust, passionate community have allowed the Steam Deck to exist -- a handheld laptop-like PC that works with some of the best Linux tech out right now.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanna go more into this, but I wanted to kind of explain the use case for this device and what to expect through my own personal experience, being a PC gamer, a console gamer, and a Linux gamer for quite a while.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Deck is pretty big. You&#x27;re not carrying this comfortably in your pocket. It&#x27;s the kind of thing you slip in a bag and play during your lunch break, not something you can pop out on a packed bus. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Build quality is very good. The touchpads are very responsive, the sticks and buttons feel just as good as modern dedicated controllers, and the speakers are actually incredible considering the form factor.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main issue I have is the screen -- I understand that the 1280x800 screen is so low res to cut down on cost and allow the device to actually run games comfortably -- but the brightness is so damn low it makes playing outdoors very unappealing. Not a fan of that at all.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The carrying case fucking sucks. Buy a new one. I&#x27;m serious. It barely fits in my bag because of how bulky and thick it is, a stark contrast from the slim form factor of the actual device. I bought a Tomtoc case today and will keep y&#x27;all updated in terms of how much easier it is to fit in a bag. Out of the box, however, the carrying case eats up so much space carrying it around in a small to medium-sized bag is incredibly unappealing. If you&#x27;re a student and have to lug around books and binders and a laptop all day, you&#x27;ll be really pressed for space and have to figure out how to properly lay everything out so it fits. It&#x27;s like playing Tetris sometimes except you really have to put the damn thing away quickly sometimes and it takes too much time.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#x27;s no USB-C port on the bottom, only the top. This makes pretty much every dock kind of weird and awkward, as you still have to plug the device in from the top. Not nearly as seamless as a Switch or even a ROG Ally (outside of the Ally being an overpriced buggy piece of shit you shouldn&#x27;t buy).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of software, I&#x27;ve been mostly pleased, but there&#x27;s a clear lack of polish in some areas. The experience docking and connecting to an external monitor is a mess, and the speakers are actually incredible considering the form factor. The default desktop mode with KDE Plasma is pretty functional, with most apps people would actually use available as Flatpaks. You really don&#x27;t need a writeable root for most Desktop Linux systems.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the things I found atrocious was actually turning on the device and registering it with my Steam account. For some reason, it refused to install properly when connected to my Wi-Fi at home, without any indication of what was going on. A re-image didn&#x27;t help; I had to literally pull out a USB-C dock and connect it directly via Ethernet. Past that initial roadblock, which would have led most people to straight-up refund the Deck, my experience was pretty good. The power management settings are really nice and granular. I even have undervolt scripts that I&#x27;m able to run for better thermals and power efficiency. Love it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some games don&#x27;t play nice, and that&#x27;s kind of the draw of PC gaming. When you&#x27;re not connected to the Internet, and you&#x27;re using a platform where tons of games have malicious DRM that demands an online connection when gaming, it becomes a huge problem. Pretty much anything with Denuvo will require you to start it once while connected to the Internet, and if you decide to twerak the game with different Proton runtimes or maybe even mess around with mods, you could get locked out of your game for a day or so. This is unacceptable; an issue even with stationary gaming PCs is exacerbated when you don&#x27;t really always have a stable connection out of the house. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you expect the occasional quirk, check to see whether the games you buy work out of the box, and try to start your games at least once at home before leaving the house to avoid Denuvo bullshit, you&#x27;ll have a good experience. Valve made a great piece of hardware and the community has help build a solid, yet flawed gaming experience through software.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;M.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>FOSS apps you should be using</title>
          <pubDate>Thu, 05 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Unknown</author>
          <link>https://zandyne.xyz/blog/fossapps/</link>
          <guid>https://zandyne.xyz/blog/fossapps/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://zandyne.xyz/blog/fossapps/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Too much modern software is designed to fuck you in the ass.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so many people put up with it. This isn&#x27;t me looking down on people from my ivory tower, I&#x27;m forced to use some of it too. BUT there&#x27;s a way out sometimes.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Free and open-source software is software where you can see all of the ingredients all laid out for you -- the code is easily accessible and available to anyone and instead of it being exclusive to a big company, it&#x27;s something anyone can contribute to. The best open source projects are massive collaborative efforts like the Linux kernel, Android, a large chunk of the modern web, etc. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And desktop apps are no different. Turns out there&#x27;s a lot of alternatives to paywall-ridden, subscription-based software that barely works and nags you about expiring trial periods. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;m going to just name applications I actually like that I make use of, and divide them by groups.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;video-editing&quot;&gt;Video editing&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortuantely, I haven&#x27;t been able to completely abandon commercial video editors. I need to use &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.blackmagicdesign.com&#x2F;products&#x2F;davinciresolve&quot;&gt;DaVinci Resolve&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; for large, potentially collaborative projects (still a great editor, btw). Outside of that, I&#x27;ve been able to move any fun personal projects and the vast majority of my video editing to open source alternatives.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.olivevideoeditor.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Olive&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; is an up and coming editor that&#x27;s pretty smooth and performant, but is still in active development and is currently technically an alpha release. Despite this, I&#x27;ve happily done tons of stuff with this editor, including complex keyframed visuals. Highly recommend this to anyone looking to just have a smooth, modern editor.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;kdenlive.org&#x2F;en&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Kdenlive&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and the technologies and frameworks that it&#x27;s made out of have been around for a while. If you like Sony Vegas-like UI, it might be the right option for you. The issue with Kdenlive is it lags behind in terms of GPU acceleration, so if you have a beefy GPU, that shit&#x27;s going to be almost completely dormant using this. Pretty solid tried and true option.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;drawing-and-painting&quot;&gt;Drawing and painting&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.gimp.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;GIMP&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; has quite a learning curve and pales in comparison in terms of functionality to Photoshop, but I&#x27;ve done a ton of image editing and visuals with it. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;krita.org&#x2F;en&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Krita&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; is a great painting software that has nice, intuitive UI. Haven&#x27;t found anything that quite matches what it can do in terms of functionality. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;inkscape.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Inkscape&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; is a vector image editing tool, and while it has a bit of a learning curve too, I&#x27;ve found it to be just as powerful as the alternatives like Adobe Illustrator. I really like this one.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;web-browsers&quot;&gt;Web browsers&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my personal opinion, there&#x27;s very little reason to actively use a browser that isn&#x27;t open-source. If you&#x27;re like me, you&#x27;re inputting a ton of personal information into these things, and personally I&#x27;d rather have something I use so extensively vetted by a community, with its vulnerabilities and functionality laid bare. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don&#x27;t have to look far:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.mozilla.org&#x2F;en-US&#x2F;firefox&#x2F;new&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Firefox&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; has been around for a while, and it&#x27;s also been &lt;em&gt;really fucking fast&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; for a while. Uses less RAM than Chrome and friends, and is a little more respectful to your privacy. There&#x27;s also a lot of &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;old.reddit.com&#x2F;r&#x2F;FirefoxCSS&#x2F;&quot;&gt;customization&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; you can do to the way it looks, if that&#x27;s your thing.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thing about most modern web browsers is they share an engine with Chrome, the Blink engine. It&#x27;s kind of concerning how the entire modern web just revolves around this one technology and if some vulnerability appears, everything suffers. Electron apps like Discord, Slack, and Spotify that are running in mini web-browsers also use Blink. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firefox stands as the one big non-Chrome browser you can use nowadays, so outside of just having a lot of practical benefits you can feel good inside knowing you&#x27;re fighting against Google&#x27;s monopoly or something. I dunno, probably won&#x27;t do much. Fuck Google.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, if you really want to use a Chromium-based browser, I recommend &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;brave.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Brave&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. It&#x27;s got the kitchen sink with it out of the box: adblocking, a BitTorrent client, and weird crypto shit that you can disable, thankfully. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;kde-connect&quot;&gt;KDE Connect&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have an Android and a Windows or Linux computer, you&#x27;re probably missing out on one of the most useful tools I&#x27;ve run into recently: &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;kdeconnect.kde.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;KDE Connect&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Being able to view battery life, get notifs on my PCs, reply to SMS messages from my PC, ring my phone, control music playback, and share files seamlessly has made my life a lot easier. You can get a Mac &amp;amp; iPhone-like integration without buying overpriced metal slabs :)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This list is by no means exhaustive, but it kinda drives me insane seeing people settle for crappy commercial software when sometimes there are perfectly good alternatives they could switch to with way less issues. Give some of them a look.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;M.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Beware of the pipeline</title>
          <pubDate>Thu, 05 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Unknown</author>
          <link>https://zandyne.xyz/blog/pipeline/</link>
          <guid>https://zandyne.xyz/blog/pipeline/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://zandyne.xyz/blog/pipeline/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;teenagers-like-validation&quot;&gt;Teenagers like validation.&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don&#x27;t need me to tell you this. Pretty much any kid from the age of like 13 all the way to... honestly, their early 20s can be absolutely obsessed with social validation. Puberty hits and kids are funneled into conformity at schools that demand they set aside a block of their day towards the same shit over and over again. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When kids are thrown into school, they simultaneously want to fit in and stand out.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If they&#x27;re forced to whip out an iron every day and throw on a stuffy uniform, they&#x27;ll wear shoes that slightly push the limits of the dress code. Fuck it, I might be forced to wear a polo and khakis every day but I&#x27;m still gonna throw on my Yeezys. At the same time, if someone talks shit about them, they might just show up with a different pair of sneakers just to feel acknowledged.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is just a normal part of being a teenager. 
Same thing applies to politics at that age.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The vast majority of middle-class teens in America aren&#x27;t really endowed with years of experience working and engaging with the real world. When there are really no consequences to strong opinions you pick up on the Internet, it becomes real easy to get sucked into an unhealthy feedback loop of bad takes.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#x27;re a fucking loser like I was in high school, you probably don&#x27;t have a lot to boast or show off. Fashion isn&#x27;t really something some teens (especially those dealing with poverty) care about, and you can&#x27;t even get academic clout because you&#x27;re just above average and not top of class. That&#x27;s a lot of kids, and for a lot of kids, the way they stand out -- the way they feel a sense of belonging with a larger group -- is by seeing smug videos with politics contrary to what they hear around them and following suit.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#x27;s opening YouTube in 2015 to watch Ben Shapiro own stupid latte-drinking college students.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;textCenter&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe
        src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube-nocookie.com&#x2F;embed&#x2F;vY4YgmcWuPM&quot;
        allow=&quot;accelerometer; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot;
        webkitallowfullscreen
        mozallowfullscreen
        allowfullscreen&gt;
    &lt;&#x2F;iframe&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;teens-favorite-form-of-self-validation-can-often-be-contrarianism&quot;&gt;Teens&#x27; favorite form of self-validation can often be contrarianism.&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can&#x27;t stress enough how widespread these corny ass liberal owning videos were (and, honestly still are) back in 2014-2017. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While before I had been around more conservative, white cultures due to where elementary and middle school were located, as well as church, high school was different. If you live in an urban, fairly liberal, black neighborhood and region like I did post middle school, it&#x27;s really easy to look at the left-leaning beliefs of everyone around you -- parents, teachers, friends -- and respond in turn with &amp;quot;counter-culture&amp;quot; beliefs about how everyone around you is bluepilled.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They don&#x27;t know that transgenderism is a lie! &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They think racism is real... and yet all they talk about is race!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simple, logical conclusions you can reach from watching too much Steven Crowder and Ben Shapiro, pretty mild neoconservative types that got a stranglehold on 2010s YouTube. It&#x27;s not a coherent ideology, it&#x27;s just pointing and laughing at people that are framed as silly dishonestly.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Eventually, though, I started to get curious: What exactly ARE these people&#x27;s beliefs?&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What became a matter of sitting down and watching hours of SJW owned compilations turned into looking at conservative subreddits. Looking at Discord while it was in its early days. Just saying shit and being validated by my own friend group which had no real coherent beliefs either but thought the things I was saying were cool.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feeling out of place in high school, still dealing with puberty, depression, and (in retrospect) gender dysphoria, I found a new &lt;em&gt;thing&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; to be known by. I was the kid that raised their hand in class to debate the teacher. Started out as simple things like fervently arguing against rent control despite never having paid any or worked a job in my life, but eventually, I got dragged into arguing for IQ differences in races. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scrolling through old &#x2F;pol&#x2F; threads, learning about IQ tier lists where Ashkenazi Jews and Anglos were at top and my own, disgusting, mangy race were at the bottom, sitting in edgelord DMs where I built up tolerance for walls of slurs, and eventually starting and obsessively engaging with threads myself. 4chan, 8chan, Reddit, Discord, YouTube comments sections, I was everywhere.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it was so fucking EASY to just &lt;em&gt;happen&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. When you&#x27;re convinced you know the truth, and when every white bald charlatan with a mic is calling you red-pilled, you don&#x27;t even question it. &lt;strong&gt;That&#x27;s why I don&#x27;t understand the surprise and bewilderment at a lot of kids getting swept up into the alt-right.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; I&#x27;m not defending the kind of person I was, I was a dumb 9th and 10th grader with zero work experience or meaningful real-world socialization. But you can see that it&#x27;s not unreasonable.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;teens-brains-are-developing-and-not-set-in-stone&quot;&gt;Teens&#x27; brains are developing and not set in stone.&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main thing that had me turn around was just engaging with the world around me more. As a black person, I&#x27;m already accustomed to code-switching around different people -- I&#x27;m not using tons of AAVE around white coworkers, but it&#x27;s a different story with the niggas on my block. Expand that to having to present myself as an innocuous liberal when it came to extracurricular outings or interviews or whatever, and I realized how much more comfortable and &lt;em&gt;genuine&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; I was that way. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have to admit late 2010s BreadTube was the biggest factor in me turning around. Not a huge fan of how insufferably &lt;em&gt;white&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; they can be, but seeing that same niche, yet engaging media presence on the Internet drew me away from the dredges of Chud City. Broke off a lot of friendships and left a lot of Discord servers, but nowadays I&#x27;m able to rest easy knowing I consider race realism some bullshit and actually seek to improve the state of the world rather than hold it stagnant. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;m not telling ANYONE to engage with dumb, edgy teens. I get that different types of people have different levels of tolerance for that shit. But what I AM advocating for are creating healthier, more interesting communities for kids to feel &amp;quot;weird&amp;quot; and contrarian in. Don&#x27;t let them act like me.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;M.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Video games aren&#x27;t art</title>
          <pubDate>Thu, 28 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Unknown</author>
          <link>https://zandyne.xyz/blog/videogamesarentart/</link>
          <guid>https://zandyne.xyz/blog/videogamesarentart/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://zandyne.xyz/blog/videogamesarentart/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;but-they-could-be&quot;&gt;But, they could be.&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#x27;re like me, you&#x27;ve probably seen plenty of Twitter accounts online insisting that Games Are Art and need to be taken seriously as such. Normally, this includes very mainstream, uncontroversially heralded video games that are considered classics. That&#x27;s fine, I guess. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But that&#x27;s as far as I&#x27;ve seen Gamers take this concept.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gamers want to engage solely with the positive, reaffirming aspects of games. They&#x27;re either puzzles to solve or feel good experiences that let them escape the long day at work. I get it.
&lt;em&gt;But video games as a medium have become nothing but toys.&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; I&#x27;m not saying toys are inherently bad. There are games where the entire appeal is its combat, or a fun gameplay loop. What I am saying is that there doesn&#x27;t seem to be much of a serious vested interest in games making significant artistic statements. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember the widespread reaction to Death Stranding? Rather than &amp;quot;I want to see Kojima improve&amp;quot; it was &amp;quot;Kojima is a hack&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Where&#x27;s my METAL GEAR&amp;quot;, etc. The problem is we&#x27;ve become incredibly stagnant and afraid of new artistic statements, chasing after the old and comfortable. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;copying-soul&quot;&gt;Copying soul&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a &lt;em&gt;fuckton&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; of indie games out nowadays that (respectably) try and buck the trend. My issue with the bulk of those I&#x27;ve experienced is they constantly find themselves pulling from &lt;em&gt;other games&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; as influence rather than other art forms. It&#x27;s an insulated cycle. Signalis is a great example of this. I think it&#x27;s an okay game, but it&#x27;s stuck within the trappings of Silent Hill 2 and some of its other influences like Resident Evil that I felt it lacked its own identity. Bomb Rush Cyberfunk is another game where I picked it up, enjoyed it, and realized that it was just Jet Set Radio Future at home. Not a bad game at all, but it&#x27;s also not something that&#x27;s making much of its own artistic statements.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what&#x27;s the solution? Well, look at Silent Hill 2 as an example again. That game pulls heavily from David Lynch&#x27;s discography, from Lost Highway to Blue Velvet. Akira Yamaoka was bumping Nine Inch Nails, Portishead, Metallica, and tons of other shit. Silent Hill 2 coalesced as a fusion of these creative influences, as well as the original game as a framework to build off. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since AAA games as a whole seem to care less and less about delivering anything but a positive toy-like experience, I think it&#x27;s up to these talented, passionate indie developers to really kick things off and just do what games do best: become an art form that ties many others together. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;clunkiness-jankiness-and-repetition&quot;&gt;Clunkiness, jankiness, and repetition&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;m not saying video games should necessarily all feel like scraping your balls against sandpaper, but I really do think that game design as a whole is almost scared to make characters fee l physically limited in movement or introduce friction and frustration in the way things are approached. From Software sort of does this by making their games generally pretty difficult and having a high difficulty curve, but as a whole I see more focus on seamless, smooth movement, mechanics, etc.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;persona-3-reload&quot;&gt;Persona 3 Reload&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Persona 3 Reload is currently in development as a ground-up Unreal remake of the original RenderWare PS2 title. Outside of my opinions on this game specifically being remade, or remakes in general as a concept, it&#x27;s a fact that this is something coming out in the near future. One of the things that REALLY puts me off about this game is the &amp;quot;rollback&amp;quot; mechanic introduced in the menu, that allows the player to undo mistakes they&#x27;ve made throughout the story.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In typical Atlus fan fashion, any kind of frustration with this mechanic was instantly shut down by most people. I can understand really liking the direction of the remake and not understanding why others don&#x27;t feel the same, but the issue here is that Persona 3 is fundamentally a game about the brevity of life on earth and making use of your time.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time never waits. It delivers all equally to the same end. You, who wish to safeguard the future, however limited it may be... You will be given one year; go forth without falter, with your heart as your guide...&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mechanically, the experience of the original is centered around making connections and Giving A Shit about the world around you. Time never waits, and you&#x27;re running out of time, so make the best use of it. That&#x27;s not to say lose your mind and panic over it, but... use your heart as your guide. Live life, and make sure when it&#x27;s over you don&#x27;t have too many regrets. A big aspect of this is &lt;em&gt;permanence&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; in the choices you make and your time management -- you can&#x27;t just roll back time, you can only adapt and move forward.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I get that Persona 3 has a load function built in, but I feel like that&#x27;s just something you expect out of JRPGs. I don&#x27;t particularly love that you can load saves from anywhere within the menu, but whatever. There&#x27;s still a difference between a load function where the intent is clearly not to constantly roll back your choices and a ROLLBACK function within the menu. It highlights a difference in priorities and a focus on immediate convenience and avoiding &amp;quot;clunk&amp;quot; over making narrative statements through mechanics.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;drakengard&quot;&gt;Drakengard&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drakengard 1 and 3 are Taro&#x27;s casual shirt and sweats projects in comparison to the work clothes, business casual Nier Replicant and Automata. They&#x27;re irreverent, disgusting, and parodic. They revel in repetition as a narrative device, because Taro looooves to hammer home the idea that killing and violence are unpleasant, and so is going through and experiencing a violent video game. This thematic statement can be perceived by just OPENING the original Drakengard and hearing the orchestral sample loops designed to drive the player insane. It&#x27;s a Dionysian experience that desensitizes you to the way we transfigure horrific acts of murder into toys. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drakengards are repetitive, like most things in its genre, and have Something To Say. You don&#x27;t have to like them, at all, but it&#x27;s one of the most popular examples I can think of of aggressive frictive elements in video games, mechanics and design that is explicitly designed at points to frustrate and upset the player. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#x27;t need every game to be a Drakengard 3, but the frustration and negative emotions it delivers should be examined as a whole and explored more within games.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;video-games-are-art-but-we-don-t-treat-them-as-such&quot;&gt;Video games ARE art, but we don&#x27;t treat them as such.&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love games. I think a lot of people don&#x27;t take them seriously. But I also refuse to retweet your dumb &lt;del&gt;animation&lt;&#x2F;del&gt;&amp;quot;games are cinema pass it on&amp;quot; posts about The Last of Us or some other movie game being Sophisticated and distancing themselves from the medium. I don&#x27;t want to call games art after a large chunk of people don&#x27;t give the slightest shit about game preservation and think anything older than 2010 demands a remake that &amp;quot;fixes&amp;quot; it. If games are art, they should be engaged with as such -- and we should try and connect with their artists and what they&#x27;re trying to say.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;M.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Linux display headaches - Why I&#x27;m stuck on Wayland</title>
          <pubDate>Tue, 26 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Unknown</author>
          <link>https://zandyne.xyz/blog/linuxdisplays/</link>
          <guid>https://zandyne.xyz/blog/linuxdisplays/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://zandyne.xyz/blog/linuxdisplays/">&lt;p&gt;My Linux history has a long association with Nvidia. Not out of choice, but just because at the time I didn&#x27;t really know Nvidia had some issues on the platform. I needed a low profile GPU for the low end OEM PC I owned at the time, and popping in a GT 1030 seemed like the right choice. At the time, I was daily driving Windows anyway, and never had to even &lt;em&gt;think&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; about whether or not my displays would work, hardware acceleration would work, etc.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Switched to Linux, and on the surface things seemed to be smooth, but then the issues hit. Keep in mind this was around 2018-2019.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hardware acceleration didn&#x27;t work, PERIOD. Outside of mpv&#x2F;VLC.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That specific card doesn&#x27;t support NVENC, which isn&#x27;t necessarily an Nvidia driver problem, but it&#x27;s frustrating how they ship out cards without such a useful feature.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kernel updates would frequently break shit. Some days I&#x27;d be greeted with a black screen, or Plymouth would be squashed or replaced with an ugly fallback visual.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;VKD3D (DirectX12 to Vulkan translation layer) experiences MAJOR peformance hits on Pascal or older cards. Also not technically something Nvidia can do anything about, but still a headache.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multiple displays with different refresh rates, VRR, and fractional scaling never worked.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The desktop in general was noticeably choppier than Windows.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;ve also had headaches with Nvidia Optimus on older Thinkpads. Jesus Christ, I never want to return to that again. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of these pain points, some of which self-imposed for using old hardware, have permanently burned me and made me reluctant to use Nvidia on Linux hardware. Despite this, I still use a &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.amazon.com&#x2F;PNY-NVIDIA-Quadro-Professional-Graphics&#x2F;dp&#x2F;B06X9PW5DZ&quot;&gt;low profile Quadro&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; in my NAS&#x2F;media server. Nvidia&#x27;s nice for that use case, since they offer very power efficient cards with solid encoders. Even then, I&#x27;m considering whether or not I should just replace that thing with a Radeon.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AMD GPUs have a mountain of issues, like their lack of focus on compute and non-gaming workloads, but almost every issue I run into on AMD I&#x27;ve found workarounds for. I use DaVinci Resolve and it works fine on AMD nowadays with OpenCL, OBS streaming and recording works fine, and whenever I get bored and decide to work with Stable Diffusion that also works fine. I&#x27;m not moving away from their offerings anytime soon, and I just hope they take some of their issues more seriously.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I bought a 6600 XT months ago and it&#x27;s been an almost seamless experience. The only problems with the GPU are actual documented problems with the specific model I have, like not working in the PCIe x16 slot properly without lowering it in BIOS to x8 speeds, and the occasional crash in two specific games (&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.protondb.com&#x2F;app&#x2F;2058180&quot;&gt;Judgment&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.protondb.com&#x2F;app&#x2F;2058190&quot;&gt;Lost Judgment&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;). I also have a Steam Deck which has given me an issue-free gaming experience on the same GPU architecture (RDNA2). Life is good.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#x27;s nuance to the GPU conundrum on Linux, and I&#x27;m not trying to present AMD as the no-brainer option in all cases, but I &lt;em&gt;cannot&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; emphasize enough how it works so much better for me.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;M.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>My disconnect from Black culture -- and how I reclaimed it</title>
          <pubDate>Fri, 22 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Unknown</author>
          <link>https://zandyne.xyz/blog/blackculture/</link>
          <guid>https://zandyne.xyz/blog/blackculture/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://zandyne.xyz/blog/blackculture/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I&#x27;m black.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is pretty damn obvious if you did a cursory look at any of my social media, this website, whatever. But yeah, I&#x27;m black. And I&#x27;m slowly coming around to accepting that.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You see, as a kid, I was raised in pretty white areas at school that weren&#x27;t overtly and obviously racist, but more subtly and uncomfortably bigoted at points. The occasional comment about how my nose is too big, my skin is too dark to look nice, how &amp;quot;people like me don&#x27;t speak English&amp;quot;, it goes on and on. Whatever. My point is, not the best kind of environment for a black boy in America.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was homeschooled for a year in my life and became incredibly unashamed at expressing my thoughts and being generally friendly to the people around me. When I got looked at like I was crazy after re-entering real school (because homeschooled kids lack social cues most of the time), I quickly wanted nothing more than to fit in with the other kids.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things got so bad when I was really young that my self-image was that of a white kid. Tried to get my name legally changed to whatever corny ass white names I could think of at the time, and grew angry at my hair not following the same pattern as the kids around me. I wanted to fit in, but obviously that didn&#x27;t really work out.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I&#x27;ve lived a pretty comfortable lower-middle class life. Parents are together and have a healthy relationship, sisters both have their quirks but enjoy my presence, and I&#x27;ve got about 6 certificates, a nice-looking resum, and a couple credits working towards my bachelor&#x27;s. But I think this was my downfall, at the same time. You see, I lacked the upbringing of even a lot of my Black peers in high school. They had to worry about whether or not the water would be running at home, I was concerned with dumb shit like my Gentoo installation at home breaking. And this kinda pulled me into the alt-right later on in life.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;...More on that later.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, something clicked towards the end of high school, going into college, where I realized that a lot of my dysphoric feelings were because of:
A. the fact that the gender binary didn&#x27;t really work for me.
B. I&#x27;m black, and not white.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So my twenties are gonna be a needed reclaiming of my own culture. That&#x27;s probably the reason behind my excessive use of nigga :)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;M.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
